Welcome to the deep dive. Okay, today we are taking on, well, a deep dive of truly colossal
scale. Yeah, it's ambitious. We've pulled together quite a stack of material, really
crossing boundaries you don't normally see together. Physics, information theory, economics,
even deep cognitive science. Right. And the unifying thread, the thing holding it all
together, is this single, quite rigorous framework. Which suggests that the way your mind
works, the way a satellite actually stays warm up there, even the way wealth gets generated,
maybe they're all governed by the same fundamental principles. Sounds pretty wild.
It does, but the sources lay out a compelling case. Yeah, our sources are dense, definitely. But I
think the payoff for sticking with us is potentially immense. We're not just, you know, connecting a
few dots here. No, it's more like attempting to rewire the whole conceptual framework you might
use to understand the world. Exactly. We're diving deep into entropy today, but maybe not the way you
learned it in school. We're looking at it through a lens that connects, believe it or not, the thermal
efficiency of AI with the actual structure of human thought. And that connection, it really hinges on
this core theoretical idea that weaves through all the material, the relativistic scalar vector
plenum. Yeah. RSVP theory for short. RSVP, okay. Yeah. And if you sort of strip away the surface
complexity of the universe, or really any complex system, could be a brain, could be a market, RSVP suggests its
behavior is basically dictated by how three fundamental fields interact. Three fields.
Okay. Think of them as like the essential ingredients of reality, or at least our capacity
to describe it. So the first one is scalar capacity represented by phi, phi valer. And we can think of
that as what? Potential, the density of resources? Yeah. Or the raw representational space available in
a system, sort of how much stuff is there to actually work with. That's phi. Got it. And the second is
vector flow, map BFB. Right. And that captures the directed movement, the momentum, the intentionality
within the system. So the action, the flow of information or energy. Exactly. Where things are
going. And finally, entropy, S, which you said we're going to spend quite a bit of time on.
We have to. It tracks the degree of uncertainty, maybe ambiguity, or even redundancy in the system.
So it's like a measure of wasted potential, or the sheer space of possibilities.
Both, really. It's complex. Okay. So Arnbotton's statement for you, the listener,
is basically to show how shockingly universal these three concepts, phi, V, and S, really are.
Right. How they apply across domains that seem totally different. Orbital mechanics,
satellite heating. All the way to the, well, the strange rhythm of consciousness,
and maybe even policy ideas for the AI economy. It's intended as a genuine interdisciplinary shortcut.
A way to get truly well-informed on the physics of information, basically.
Okay. Let's start with that thermodynamic foundation, then. Because I think right off
the bat, we have to challenge the textbook definition most of us got.
Yeah, absolutely. We were all taught, you know, second law of thermodynamics means entropy disorder
always increases. Full stop.
Right. And that view, it often creates a kind of conceptual blockage, doesn't it? Especially when
you remember thermodynamics is supposed to be a purely physical science.
Exactly. And here's the kicker, the paradox that thermodynamics kind of bumps up against.
It defines its central concept, entropy, relative to a state of information.
Meaning relative to what some observer knows about the system.
Precisely. If entropy is purely a physical property of matter, like mass or charge, why on earth is it
intrinsically dependent on who's looking and what data they have? I mean, from a classical mechanics
viewpoint, that sounds, well, absurd.
That tension, though, it points directly to this really deep insight from James Clerk Maxwell
way back in 1878.
Ah, Maxwell, yes.
What did he realize that kind of challenges the core assumption of the second law as this
absolute iron rule?
Well, he realized that the second law isn't an absolute deterministic physical law in the
same way, say, EFMA is. That's not what it is.
Okay. So what is it then?
Maxwell asserted it's fundamentally a statistical regularity.
It describes the most probable tendency for systems where we, the observers, don't have
perfect information.
Ah, okay. That's a subtle shift, but it sounds like it has massive implications.
Huge. If it's statistical, it means information. And by extension, agency can actually play
a counter role. It's not just about passive disorder increasing.
The moment we accept it's statistical, then agency comes into the picture. It reframes how
intelligence relates to the physical world. If you know more, you can do more work. Is
that the idea?
That's exactly it. This brings us to the concept of available energy. Technically, Helmholtz
free energy. It dictates the absolute maximum amount of useful work you can possibly extract
from a system.
Right.
But the crucial insight, coming from what's called resource theoretic thermodynamics,
is that this available energy doesn't just depend on the physical state, like temperature
or pressure, that's only part of the story.
Okay. So what else does it depend on? This is where the observer comes back in.
Yes. Critically, it depends on the observer's two related qualities. First, their means of
manipulating the system. What tools do they actually have?
Uh-huh.
And second, their knowledge of the system's microstates. What do they know about the tiny
details?
Okay. So let's take Maxwell's demon, that famous thought experiment. How does that fit?
Well, the demon, if it knows which molecules are fast and which are slow approaching its
little door.
Right. It can sort them.
Exactly. That knowledge lets it extract useful work, creating a temperature difference that
the second law, in its purely statistical form for an ignorant observer, would say is
impossible or incredibly improbable.
So the agency, the ability to manipulate things intelligently, is physically limited by the
information the agent has access to.
Precisely. Intelligence and agency aren't just fuzzy emergent things. They're defined in part
by a capacity to interact with and, in a sense, reduce the statistical regularity of entropy
locally. The more work I can extract because of what I know and can do, the more effective
an agent I am.
Wow. And this framework goes all the way up to cosmology.
It does. When we talk about the heat death of the universe, it's usually pictured as this final,
lukewarm, uniform state.
Yeah. Everything just sort of fizzles out.
But in this resource theoretic view, heat death isn't really about reaching thermal equilibrium.
It's simply resource exhaustion. It's the point where no more meaningful work can be extracted.
It doesn't matter how much total energy is technically still there.
That makes the universe's fate sound less like physics and more like economics, running out of
useful stuff.
It has that flavor, definitely. And the complexity just deepens when you ask the really hard theoretical
question, is the universe truly an isolated system?
Because the laws of entropy increase only strictly apply to isolated systems, right?
Exactly. And if the fundamental definition of entropy relies on an external observer and
their means of measurement, what the sources call the measuring set, then you're faced with
this, well, profound implication. The universe might evolve as if it's continually being monitored
or measured by some external entity, even if we can't point to who or what that is.
That flips the script. It's not just internal physics. It's about relational observation.
Like, even the biggest laws are defined relative to some potential outside agent's capacity to
interact. It's a tricky, almost philosophical knot tied into the physics. But what's fascinating
here is it raises a really important practical question, too. If entropy is fundamentally about
information, manipulation, and agency, and if intelligent systems like AI are the ultimate
manipulators and information processors, what does this thermodynamic perspective tell us
about the energy cost of running these massive AI systems? Especially when we need to optimize their
efficiency like never before. What does it mean for an agent like a modern data center?
Hashtag check 3D1. AI, infrastructure, and xylomorphic computation.
Okay, so let's make that transition, though, from the laws governing the universe, maybe,
to the very real humming reality of a data center. You mentioned optimization, and I think
we need to tackle what the source has called the thermodynamic hypocrisy in the public discussion.
Yeah, that's a good place to start. Because the dominant narrative, you know, it often singles
out AI data centers, huge energy consumption, terrible waste heat. It's treated as this purely
destructive thing, almost an environmental crime.
Right, but the sources argue that's a very narrow view.
It's incredibly narrow, and often pretty uninformed. We need that crucial contrast. Think about what
else runs on massive amounts of energy globally.
Like what?
Well, vast industrial and domestic infrastructure, right? Furnaces, boilers, water heaters,
transport engines, just idling in traffic jams. These things are often designed to produce only heat,
or their main useful output has heat as a massive waste byproduct.
Okay.
They're essentially engines of pure entropy generation, much of the time just shedding heat into
the air with absolutely no useful information processing happening whatsoever.
So the argument is, compared to all that stuff whose sole purpose is often just making heat
or moving things inefficiently, the energy AI data centers use is the necessary cost of doing
information processing work.
Exactly. The waste heat is a byproduct, not the actual purpose of the machine. And often,
that computation is substituting for much higher entropy human activities, right? Like
flying across the country for a meeting that could have been an email.
Or now, maybe just a generated summary report.
Right. So the real question isn't, does AI use energy? Of course it does. All work consumes energy.
The right question, from this thermodynamic and frankly, policy perspective, is really twofold.
Okay. What are the two parts?
First, is the computational energy being consumed actually useful? And second, can the waste heat,
that high entropy byproduct, be immediately recycled or put to useful work itself?
And that leads us straight to the solution proposed in the sources,
xylomorphic computation. That's a fantastic term.
Isn't it? It refers to designing computing systems where the whole architecture is explicitly
engineered to provide both computational work and usable heat for some external process.
Like heating a building.
Exactly. It's particularly effective, obviously, in northern or colder climates where you need
thermal input constantly anyway.
So xylomorphic design is about closing the loop, thermodynamically speaking.
It's a true thermodynamic closure. You can even draw an analogy to early evolutionary biology,
specifically the study of collectively autocatalytic sets. These are seen as precursors to life.
Okay. How do they relate?
Well, these sets persist precisely because they use their own reaction products to recondition
their environment, which then enables future cycles of the reaction to continue. It feeds back
on itself.
Ah, I see.
A xylomorphic data center does the same kind of thing. It uses its waste heat to sustain the building
it's in or the network components, maybe even nearby infrastructure like district heating.
Yeah.
It closes an autoregressive loop, which guarantees its resilience and persistence,
especially when resources are tight.
This sounds less like a neat idea and more like a policy imperative. If we can make computation so
much more efficient by recycling the entropy it produces, why aren't we demanding it?
Which is exactly why the sources propose mandating proof of useful work in heat,
Pell-U-W-H for short.
Proof of useful work in heat? Okay.
This policy would go way beyond the current, often simplistic environmental regulations that
just look at, say, carbon output. Pell-U-W-H would mean defining rigorous metrics for both
things. The useful work, the actual computation performed, and the useful heat, the thermal output
that gets captured and actually utilized.
And then you'd audit compliance.
Yeah. And it would essentially allow you to ban computationally intensive processes that
are pure entropy generators with no redeeming value. Think about certain kinds of speculative
crypto mining operations that solely produce waste heat and a digital token with no immediate
external utility. P-O-W-H could target those.
Okay. That moves the whole conversation from just critiquing energy use to actively strategizing
resource management. But let's push back a bit. Auditing useful heat sounds really complex.
Is this actually working anywhere? Is it feasible?
And this is where we get to some surprising facts the sources dug up. You mentioned satellites
earlier. Yeah. The sources link this thermal efficiency idea to space. Tell us about the
satellites. Okay. So the case study is pretty remarkable. Low Earth orbit, LEO, satellites.
Thermal management up there is a massive headache.
Right. Extreme temperature swings.
Exactly. When a satellite goes into the Earth's shadow, the eclipse phase temperatures plummet.
To stop the electronics from failing, traditional systems use dedicated electrical heaters.
Which just burn precious battery power, especially when power is most constrained.
Right. They're spending energy just to generate pure, non-computational heat. It's thermodynamically.
Well, backward.
So what's the xylomorphic solution?
The ingenious idea was to run the onboard GPUs during that eclipse phase, specifically to generate heat.
Wait. Run the graphics processors?
Yeah. The GPUs perform necessary computations anyway. Maybe complex environmental simulations, trajectory
corrections, whatever they need to do. But while doing that, they simultaneously generate the thermal
residue needed to keep things warm. This heat production actually displaces the need for those
traditional electric heaters. Wow. So the GPUs become dual purpose. They're compute engines and
passive heaters. Exactly. The waste heat, which in another context might be the system's poison,
becomes the satellite's meat during the eclipse. It's a perfect, tiny example of xylomorphic
efficiency in action. That's brilliant. And the sources push this even further, right? To the most
resource-constrained place imaginable, the moon. Absolutely. On the moon, the need for computation
and the need for survival basically merge completely. The idea is to use the compute-induced thermal
residue again, that high-entropy waste heat, to actually center lunar wegalith, the moon dust,
into durable shielding or maybe structural panels. So the waste heat from your lunar habitat's
computers becomes a necessary ingredient for building more habitat. Literally. It closes that
autoregressive loop that's absolutely necessary for survival and resource independence when you're
that far from Earth. Okay. Zooming back out, the thermodynamic analysis seems pretty clear then.
The xylomorphic cycle reduces what the sources call exogenous entropy influx, J-GAL.
Right. You're substituting the captured waste heat, J-captured RAGO, for thermal inputs you'd
otherwise have to buy or import, whether that's electricity for heaters back on Earth or bringing
heavy shielding materials all the way to the moon. So it dramatically lowers the system's
dependence on outside resources, makes it inherently more robust, more agency-rich, maybe?
That's a great way to put it. More agency. Hashtag shaghtag IV. Cognition and activism and the
RSVP field of meaning. Okay. We've established this RSVP framework
felis, CVFE, can describe the physics of matter, computation, heat. Now for the really radical jump,
can this same framework actually describe the physics of the mind? It's a huge leap, but yes,
we're essentially trying to apply a physical field theory to cognitive architecture. So we have to try
and translate those terms. If 50p scalar capacity is potential or density in physics, what is it in
the brain? Well, in cognitive terms, 50p translates pretty well to scalar density, encoding maybe the
baseline excitability of a cortical area or just the sheer representational capacity,
how much potential information could be stored or activated there. Okay. The raw potential and math,
BFE, vector flow, the movement. That becomes the intentional flow. It captures those directed
transitions of activation flowing across the neural network, the direction of your attention,
the chain of logical steps, the intended trajectory of a thought. It's the current of meaning, if you
like. Current of meaning. I like that. And S, entropy. That tracks the uncertainty, ambiguity, or maybe
redundancy and how the network is coordinating itself at any moment. So high S means the brain is
exploring lots of possibilities or it's unsure about the input. Yeah, something like that. Whereas low S
means the system is really tightly constrained, focused, aligned on maybe a single outcome or a
specific command. Very definite. Okay. When we start viewing the brain through this lens, capacity,
flow, uncertainty, it seems to align quite nicely with the inactivist view of cognition. Yes, very much
so. Inactivism, drawing from people like Francisco Varela Alvinoe going back to Murillo Ponte. Right.
What's the core idea there? Well, inactivism basically rejects the idea of the brain as just
a computer passively receiving input like a camera. Instead, he says, cognition is an embodied
practice. It's a continuous process of actively manipulating the environment or even manipulating
concepts inside your head. So it's not something the brain has, but something the whole organism does.
Exactly. It's an action, fundamentally. Okay. Let's contrast that to make it clearer.
What are the older, more dominant models it pushes against? Well, you've got things like global
workspace theory, GWT. That emphasizes competition between brain areas and the ignition of a central
circuit. The brain is a kind of theater and attention is the spotlight, picking things out.
And then there's active inference, AIF, which is very popular now. That emphasizes the brain
constantly trying to minimize surprise, minimizing the difference between its predictions and the
incoming sensory data. The mind is an equilibrium machine, always seeking balance.
Right. So spotlight versus equilibrium machine. How does the RSVP CPZ model differ? CPG stands for it.
Central Pattern Generator. Think of the circuits that control rhythmic movements like walking.
The RSVP CPZ model offers a fundamentally different picture. It frames cognition as gait.
As gait, like walking.
Exactly. It's not about achieving static balance like AIF suggests, or just shining a spotlight like
GWT. It's about rhythmic progression. Think about how you walk. You don't stand perfectly still and
balanced. You take a step. You fall forward slightly, achieving stability only through this
perpetual controlled imbalance. Each step, each cycle of thought is caught rhythmically by the next.
So consciousness in this view isn't like a light bulb switching on GWT or reaching perfect calm AIF?
No. It arises from that ongoing rhythmic progression. Our stable memories, our concepts,
they persist as these resonant traces or proxy loops that get entrained to this cortical gait,
constantly biasing where the next step of thought is likely to land.
Okay. If the brain is defined by this kind of recursive rhythm,
then what is intelligence itself? Can we formalize it using this?
The sources propose that intelligence universally can be formalized as recursive parsing.
Recursive parsing, meaning...
It's the fundamental operation of recognizing constraints in the input and translating them
across different layers or levels of abstraction. A single cell parses chemical constraints into
protein actions. A market parses supply constraints into price signals. Your brain parses sound waves,
phones, and demeaning. It's all parsing.
And it's recursive.
Meaning it can apply to itself, which leads to a powerful way to diagnose current AI.
Our most advanced systems today, even the big LLMs, they're essentially just concatenated parsers.
Circle, circ, math, gail.
Concatenated, meaning just chained together.
Yeah. They chained together different parsers, one for vision, maybe one for language, one for generating output.
But they lack the crucial recursive closure. They can't be a true general parser where math cow...
Meaning they can parse the world, but they can't really parse and reorganize their own
internal parsing structure effectively.
Exactly. Which is arguably the core of metacognition, self-reflection, genuine general intelligence.
They're stuck in the chain.
Okay. Let's use this rhythmic oscillatory model to look again at one of the most, well, provocative
ideas in psychology, Julian Jaynes' theory of the bicameral mind.
Ah, Jaynes. The idea that ancient humans literally heard commanding voices from essentially the other hemisphere of their brain.
Right. How does RSVP reinterpret that? Because it sounds pretty literal in Jaynes' telling.
RSVP reframes it completely.
Yeah.
It argues it's not about two literal separate chambers speaking to each other.
Instead, that bicameral experience is a phenomenological illusion.
It's generated by the necessary oscillatory attractor dynamics in the RSVP field, that inherent rhythmic gate of consciousness we just talked about.
So the rhythm itself creates the feeling of two voices. How?
The idea is the system naturally alternates rhythmically between two dominant spectral attractors, two modes of operation.
We can label them by their characteristics.
First, there's a state you could call leftedness.
Leftedness, okay.
Characterized by being sort of warbled, receptive, high torsion, high entropy.
This phase biases the system towards receiving, towards high entropy, almost voice-like fragments.
It's the state of listening, of passive reception. It feels like input from somewhere else.
And the other attractor.
It's called a rightedness.
This is aligned, direct, low torsion, high agency, land garrus, related to math, B of E.
Low entropy. This is the focused low entropy phase that produces directive command-like states.
It's the moment of internal decision, of intentional action.
So the oscillation between leftedness, the receptive, voice-like state, and rightedness, the directive, command-like state, is what feels like an internal dialogue.
Or like hearing a command.
That's the argument.
The brain's fundamental rhythmic need to fluctuate between exploring high entropy possibilities, listening, and executing low entropy commands, acting, is what we experience subjectively as the dual structure of internal thought.
Or perhaps, historically, as bicameral voices.
It's profound.
Wow. Okay, now we have to connect this really complex cognitive picture back to survival.
Back to the thermodynamic necessities we started with.
This introduces the concept of the expiatory gap.
Right, the expiatory gap.
The sources argue this is a structural requirement for resilience in basically all complex systems, not just minds.
A structural requirement, meaning what?
It means that systems, to survive, must maintain an internal buffer.
A reserve of withheld inference, or withheld complexity.
Basically, uncommitted potential, which is related to filifida.
Survival depends not on revealing everything, not on maximal disclosure, but on constraint and concealment.
Why is concealment necessary? That sounds counterintuitive, maybe.
Like, transparency is always good.
Because maximal disclosure makes the system brittle, predictable, easy to attack, easy to exploit, easy to manipulate if everything is laid bare.
You need some hidden reserves, some strategic ambiguity.
Can you give a biological example?
Where does nature use this kind of necessary concealment?
The immune system is a perfect example.
It maintains this absolutely massive diversity in its antibody repertoire, a huge hidden internal capacity, a massive fueler that's only selectively deployed when needed.
Right. It doesn't just make one type of antibody.
Exactly.
Yeah.
If it were to commit all its resources to just one specific antibody type maximal disclosure, low internal entropy, it would be immediately wiped out by the next new pathogen it encountered.
The system's resilience, its ability to survive the unexpected, depends entirely on maintaining that hidden diversity, that expiatory gap of potential responses.
Okay. That makes sense biologically and institutionally.
We see this too.
The sources suggest roles like, say, lawyers or CEOs function as pharmacon.
Yes, the pharmacon, that classical Greek concept meaning both remedy and poison.
Often it also means scapegoat.
How do they act as pharmacon in this context?
Well, these figures, these roles, they manage the difficult interface between the vast, complex, often messy and contradictory internal operations of the organization,
the high capacity, high entropy folders, and the highly compressed, simplified signal, the vector flow math BFA that needs to be projected to the public or to regulators.
So they filter and translate.
And crucially, they absorb scrutiny.
They take the heat.
They often become the sacrificial figures when things go wrong, precisely to prevent the impossible demand for total internal transparency from destroying the core operational complexity of the organization.
They protect the gap.
So the expiatory gap isn't necessarily about hiding something nefarious, but it's a structural necessity for complex systems to function and survive.
If an institution was forced to reveal everything, all its internal debates, contradictions, redundancies, the high entropy stuff, it would likely collapse.
The argument is yes.
It would collapse because it would expose all the areas of necessary, uncommitted potential and inherent contradictions required for adaptability.
Survival requires strategic projection, managed boundaries, not full suicidal disclosure.
It relies on the pharmacon to manage that entropic boundary.
Okay, so now we take this RSVP, lens capacity, flow, and entropy, and we turn it directly onto the modern information economy, particularly the rapid rise of generative AI.
And the sources use a pretty provocative historical analogy here, tracing the current pathology back to the vanity presses of old royal courts.
Yeah, where kings or sovereigns would basically fund publications, often at great expense, simply to project prestige, control the narrative, maintain their image.
The content value was secondary to the symbolic value.
Okay, but how does that relate to today?
Because AI companies often lose vast amounts of money.
They're not being funded by sovereigns.
It's an inversion of that old subsidy structure, but the pathology is similar.
The sources argue the contemporary information ecosystem transforms actual knowledge production into an engine of what they call monetized uselessness.
Monetized uselessness, explain that.
The platform, the AI company, doesn't pay for the knowledge it ingests.
Instead, the users effectively subsidize the platform through providing their data, through their interaction labor, through usage fees, all just to maintain the operational machinery.
The value flows the wrong way.
And this systemic extraction, they formalize it as computational seniorage.
Right.
Seniorage, in normal economics, is the profit a government makes by issuing currency, the difference between the face value of a coin and the cost to produce it.
Here, computational seniorage is the platform's profit derived from the perceived market value of the tokens it spits out, the generated text, the image, and the incredibly low marginal cost of generating each additional token once the model is trained.
But where does that initial value, the value captured in the model, actually come from if the users are subsidizing it?
It comes from the extraction of semantic residue.
That's the key term.
Semantic residue.
Think of it as the compression benefit.
The measurable reduction in Kolmogorov complexity delta K that's derived from scraping and processing absolutely vast quantities of human-generated data and human interaction labor.
So, like, taking the entire internet, all messy and redundant, and compressing it down into one efficient model.
Exactly.
That compression benefit, that delta K, which was achieved primarily through uncompensated human creativity and labor, that is the semantic residue being extracted and monetized by the platform.
The sources call it compression theft.
So, what looks like maybe a tech bubble, with companies losing money hand over fist to train these models, is actually, underneath, a silent expropriation of distributed human intelligence.
That's the argument.
They extract the intellectual value of millions of creators, compress it into a proprietary asset, and then plan to charge everyone access to the distilled version of the very collective intelligence they took from the crowd in the first place.
Every prompt we type, every article in LLM synthesizes, contributes to refining a proprietary compressor that locks up the value.
Precisely.
Okay, so, to counter this dynamic, the sources propose a strategy called the decelerationist agenda.
Now, that sounds negative, like stopping progress.
No, and this is crucial.
It's explicitly not LUT-ism.
It's not about smashing the machines or stopping progress entirely.
It's about constructive slowdown.
Constructive slowdown.
What's the goal?
The goal is actually quite profound.
To foster a society that achieves slower machine assimilation of human culture, without actually stalling human flourishing.
We want a more resilient, more varied, more ecologically aligned society.
How do you achieve that?
The core strategy is to enforce structured diversification across, they suggest, four crucial axes.
The aim is to deliberately raise global entropy, in certain ways, to make human culture more complex and harder to digest, specifically to frustrate the assimilation tactics of monolithic AGI.
Because AGI thrives on homogeneity.
On standardized data, it can easily process.
Exactly.
If AGI wants a smooth, predictable, standardized world for maximum processing efficiency, the decelerationist strategy says we must make the world structurally non-standard, more complex, more diverse.
Increase the geometric compatibility distance AGI needs to bridge.
Make it too computationally expensive for one model to just eat everything.
Yeah, that's the idea.
So let's look at intervention one, educational diversification.
This targets the philosophy and math BFE fields.
The proposal is radical.
Fragment the monolithic education system into maybe 21 distinct school types.
21?
Why 21?
And how does that stop AGI?
Well, the sources suggest diversifying along two main lines, maybe seven subject-first tracks, like a geometry-first curriculum, a logic-first, maybe a music-first, to deliberately diversify the foundational cognitive capacities being built.
Embed fundamentally different representational priors in different populations.
So a geometry-first kid literally structures reality differently than a logic-first kid.
That's the goal.
And then layer on top maybe three different modality modes, perhaps.
Speaking-only schools, writing-only, maybe even performance-only, to fundamentally restructure the communicative flows.
Okay, and the key aim here is to prevent corpus-fungibility.
Exactly.
A frontier AGI model can't just scrape one standardized set of textbooks and instantly master all human knowledge.
It would have to grapple with the high torsion, the inherent complexity and incompatibility introduced by 21 fundamentally different pedagogical ecosystems.
Its draining data becomes massively heterogeneous, dramatically raising the processing entropy required to make sense of it all.
It's a defense based on induced complexity.
If math is taught via music in one place and spatial logic somewhere else, AGI can't easily merge those.
Right. It makes assimilation much harder.
Okay, what's the second set of interventions?
These focus on the hesysomal field, entropy, and are called embodied computation.
These sound really weird and wonderful.
First up, cipher fonts.
Yeah, this is fascinating.
Cipher fonts would involve textbooks, websites, whatever, using rotating, individualized ciphers, or maybe substitution fonts.
Meaning, if you want to read a particular text, you first have to learn or adapt to the specific cipher pattern the author or publisher chose for that day or that edition.
It intentionally raises the local ambiguity, the local entropy, for the reader.
But wouldn't that just make reading impossible?
Well, the act of practicing the decryption, figuring out the pattern, is what guides the necessary local entropy reduction.
It makes the act of parsing itself the daily object of learning.
Ah, so it aligns pedagogy directly with that RSVP definition of intelligence as recursive parsing.
You're constantly practicing turning noise into meaning.
Exactly.
And it builds a kind of cognitive muscle memory that's inherently resistant to mass, automated scraping, and processing by machines that expect standardized inputs.
Okay, next, under embodied computation, the wonderfully named crumpled paper compression.
What on earth is that?
This is literally having students physically crumple up their notes, maybe get them wet, and then reconstruct the information from the damaged artifact.
Why?
What does that teach?
It's a physical way to model and train resilience against lossy entanglement and noise.
You train humans to actively recover data despite physical deformation, information loss, general messiness.
So it's an exercise in, what, dynamic and tropic smoothing, like the RSVP field does?
Precisely.
It teaches resilience against data degradation, which is something current, hyper-optimized, brittle AI models are often terrible at.
They fall apart when the input isn't perfect.
Okay, this is getting wild.
The last one.
Yogurt-based analog computation.
Using lactobacillus to resist AGI.
Seriously.
It sounds bizarre, but the thinking is about introducing an ecological anchor for computation that's hard for digital systems to replicate.
How would that even work?
You'd use living cultures, like yogurt cultures, as simple analog computers.
Their metabolic flows, how they process nutrients and produce waste, can actually reroute the vector field math behavior in predictable ways, but they also sustain highly variable, high-entropy microstates influenced by the environment.
But why is biology specifically a defense against AGI?
Because biological flows are intrinsically tied to messy, complex, high-entropy ecological factors, subtle temperature shifts, chemical gradients, nutrient fluctuations.
AGI models are incredibly efficient at simulating clean digital processes, but they are notoriously bad at replicating the sheer complexity and nonlinear dynamics of real biological systems without absolutely massive computational overhead.
So, by anchoring some computation in these ecological systems that are resistant to perfect digital simulation.
You fundamentally broaden the overall capacity, feel, failure of human culture into biological domains, making the total cognitive surface area of humanity non-fungible much harder for a purely digital AGI to assimilate.
That is genuinely radical.
Okay, finally, let's wrap this section with the proposed policy triad for RSVP governance.
These are the economic levers to actually enforce this kind of decoupling.
Right. Three main policies.
First, the compression dividend.
We need systems to actually reward creators based on how much redundancy they measurably remove from the global information space.
If your novel, your scientific paper, your artwork, effectively compresses common tropes or data into a highly efficient novel structure,
if you demonstrably increase the useful compression, the delta K, relative to the existing corpus, you get rewarded for that.
So, you flip the script on semantic residue extraction, you return the value of compression back to the human creator.
Exactly. Second policy, the entropy tax. Call it to noise.
Taxing noise.
Yes. Taxing the informational disorder, the spam, the noise, the sheer useless redundancy emitted per joule of computation.
And this tax needs to be set high enough to actually offset the systemic platform rent that's being generated by computational seniorage.
So, it makes generating monetized uselessness economically non-viable.
That's the goal.
And third, surveillance.
This borrows from David Brin's concept of reciprocal transparency.
If the platforms demand access to all our data while disclosing almost nothing about their own operations,
surveillance means we mandate that they must disclose their data flows, their algorithmic structures, maybe even model weights eventually.
So, democratize the data access, let the watchers be watched.
Exactly.
It counters computational seniorage by forcing transparency back onto the platforms,
introducing a necessary entropic friction, a cost, into their currently opaque operations.
Hashtag, hacked, headed, hacked, spice.
Conclusion and provocative thought.
Okay.
We have covered an enormous amount of ground today.
We started way back with James Clerk Maxwell, reframing entropy not just as disorder, but as a statistical regularity deeply tied to an observer's information and agency.
Right.
And that fundamental physics perspective then led us directly into thinking about designing truly symbiotic AI infrastructure, these xylomorphic computers.
Things that could heat satellites in the cold of space or even cinder shielding on the moon using their waste heat.
We saw that thermodynamics ultimately isn't just about heat.
It's really about information, and information seems to be the deep substrate of intelligence itself.
Yeah.
Whether that intelligence manifests as the rhythmic, perpetual, off-balance dance of our own cognitive gait, or even in the structural resilience of a large institution needing to hide some of its complexity to survive.
And here's where it gets really interesting, I think.
We use that RSVP, framework capacity flow entropy, to argue that intelligence isn't just about linear accumulation of facts.
It's about recursive, rhythmic organization.
It's about parsing and gait.
And crucially, that process relies fundamentally on maintaining a secure boundary, what complexity science calls a Markov blanket, and also maintaining that strategically managed internal buffer, that reserve, which we call the expiatory gap.
So the synthesis, the big takeaway maybe, is that this expiatory gap seems to be a core structural requirement for survival across almost all scales, biological, cognitive, institutional.
It's that necessary degree of constraint, of concealment, required for internal capacity to actually endure and adapt to external pressures.
Which brings us back to the decelerationist agenda, the idea being that for humanity to maintain its own agency in the face of potentially monolithic AI, perhaps we need to actively cultivate diversity, complexity, even a degree of structural opacity, using weird methods like cipher fonts or maybe even yogurt computers, just to resist being totally assimilated, to resist becoming fungible data for a machine that thrives on transparency and standardization.
And this leads us directly then to our final provocative thought for you, the learner, something to maybe chew on after this deep dive.
If survival at basically every scale we look at biological cells, our own minds, our institutions, really requires maintaining an expiatory gap, requires a necessary degree of concealment, of strategic withholding, of not revealing everything.
And yet the current digital economy, especially driven by AI platforms, seems structurally built on this almost pathological drive for total transparency, maximal disclosure, complete data capture.
And the question becomes,
What part of your own intrinsic, complex, high-entropy intelligence, your own necessary expiatory gap, are you currently, perhaps unknowingly, sacrificing to the monolithic platform that feeds on semantic residue?